Guide to the Papers of Harmon Hendricks Goldstone 1906-1979 (bulk 1966-1979) MS 256
New-York Historical Society
Harmon Hendricks Goldstone Papers
1906-1986 (bulk 1966-1979)
New-York Historical Society
MS 256
9 Linear feet (14 boxes)
The papers of Harmon H. Goldstone focus primarily on the work of New York City's Landmarks Preservation Commission from 1968 until 1979. Goldstone's detailed journal record books, created during his tenure as Chairman of the panel, are included, as are Landmarks Designation Reports from 1973 through 1979. A few reports reflecting earlier work Goldstone did as a member of the City Planning Commission are also contained within the collection, his manuscript for History Preserved: New York City Landmarks and Historic Districts along with notes compiled in preparation of the manuscript. Other highlights include published books and pamphlets concerning New York City along with a number of clippings, photographs, and personal memorabilia.
Provenance
Bequest, 2002 and 2004.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Biographical Note
Missing Title
1911 Harmon H. Goldstone born in New York City.
1928 Graduates from Lincoln School.
1932 Receives BA from Harvard, majoring in Fine Arts.
1936 Receives Architectural degree from Columbia University School of Architecture.
1936 Joins architectural firm of Harrison & Fouilhoux (later Harrison & Abramovitz), where he helps develop the Trylon and Perisphere, symbols of the "World of Tomorrow" at the 1939 New York World's Fair. He remains for 16 years, although he leaves for a year of government service in Washington and three years in the Army as an economist and statistician.
1952 Leaves Harrison & Fouilhoux to form own architectural firm, Goldstone and Dearborn (known later as Goldstone, Dearborn & Hinz, and Goldstone and Hinz); projects include the Aquatic Bird House at the Bronx Zoo (1964), the Osborn Laboratories of Marine Sciences at the New York Aquarium at Coney Island (1965), and the remodeling of the Christie's auction house at Park Avenue and 59th Street (1977)
1961 Goldstone, then president of the Municipal Arts Society, named by Mayor Robert F. Wagner to the Committee for the Preservation of Structures of Historic and Aesthetic Importance, a forerunner of the Landmarks Preservation Commission.
1961 Goldstone also named to the City Planning Commission, the first architect in many years to serve.
1968 Goldstone succeeds Geoffrey Platt as the Chairman of the Landmarks Preservation Commission, and becomes the first to be paid a salary. On his watch, 7,271 buildings were designated for preservation. Many historic districts were authorized, including 60 blocks of Greenwich Village and 26 of SoHo. Also during his time on the panel, plans for a tower over Grand Central Terminal were rejected, touching off a legal battle that ended in a 1978 U.S. Supreme Court decision vindicating the landmarks law.
1974 Goldstone finishes tenure as Chairman of the Landmarks Preservation Commission, leaving it, in Ada Louise Huxtable's words, "at a new threshold of power and influence."
2001 Goldstone dies on February 21, 2001, at the age of 89, in New York City.
Additional information may be found in Mr. Goldstone's obituary in The New York Times, February 23, 2001.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Harmon H. Goldstone have as their primary focus the work of New York City's Landmarks Preservation Commission from 1968 until 1979. Goldstone's detailed journal record books, created during his tenure as Chairman of the panel, are included, as are Landmarks Designation Reports from 1973 through 1979. A few reports reflecting earlier work Goldstone did as a member of the City Planning Commission are also contained within the collection, his manuscript for History Preserved: New York City Landmarks and Historic Districts along with notes compiled in preparation of the manuscript. Other highlights include published books and pamphlets concerning New York City along with a number of clippings, photographs, and personal memorabilia.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following eight series:
Missing Title
Series I. Journals
Series II. Reports
Series III. Scrapbooks
Series IV. Clippings and Memorabilia
Series V. Pulications, Speeches, & Indices
Series VI. Books and Pamphlets
Series VII. Photography
Series VIII. Oversized Materials.
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
The N-YHS Library has other manuscript collections relating to historic preservation in New York including the
Margot Gayle Papers,
the Shirley Hayes Papers,
and the Carolyn Kent Papers.
The N-YHS Library also has several books co-authored by Harmon Goldstone:
Goldstone, Harmon H. and M. Dalrymple. History Preserved: A Guide to New York City Landmarks and Historic Districts. New York: Simon and Schuster, 1974. (Call Number: F128.7 G64)
Goldstone, Aline Lewis and Harmon Goldstone. Lafayette A. Goldstone; A Career in Architecture. New York, 1964. (Call Number: CT.G6245)
Goldstone also donated to the Library's collections a variety of items. The following examples include an architectural proposal, conference papers, and a children's story about preserving buildings:
Goldstone & Hinz Architects, P.C. Proposal for New Queens County Court Building: February 1989. [New York: Goldstone & Hinz Architects, [1989]]. (Call Number: F128QHD3890.N7G65)
Economic Benefits of Preserving Old Buildings: Papers from the Economic Benefits of Preserving Old Buildings Conference. Washington: Preservation Press, National Trust for Historic Preservation, 1976. (Call Number: E159.E26 1975)
Colman, Hila. Andy's Landmark House. New York: Parents' Magazine Press, [1969]. (Call Number: PZ7.C7 1969)
Architects; Central Park (New York, N.Y.); Clippings (information artifacts); Historic buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Historic districts -- New York (State) -- New York.; Historic structure reports.; Journals (accounts); Municipal government -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Reports.; Scrapbooks.; Weddings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Goldstone (Family); Goldstone, Harmon H. (Harmon Hendricks), 1911-; Grand Central Terminal (New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.). Landmarks Preservation Commission; New York (N.Y.). City Planning Commission; New York (N.Y.). Landmarks Preservation Commission
- Series I. Journals
  Scope and Contents note
  This series is composed of 27 volumes of daily summaries created by Harmon Goldstone while he served as Chairman of the Landmarks Preservation Commission (LPC) and for some months afterward. Goldstone, an architect and author, helped form the LPC during the early 1960s. The journals, in his handwriting and dated October 21, 1968 through June 25, 1974, detail day-to-day issues encountered during the early years of the organization's professional formation and structured existence through its rise to authority and serious influence. (The volumes are numbered consecutively. Numbers 14, 16 and 17, however, are not included.)
  The detailed entries are more extensive than a typical desk calendar, and Goldstone apparently designed his entries to facilitate subsequent referral. According to an entry in 1969, his diaries were being used as the basis of information disseminated at his Monday staff briefings. There are also references to his using previous entries to validate recollections and to provide information for subsequent analyses. It appears from the breadth and variety of Goldstone's entries that these diaries contain all that transpired in the LPC office on any given day. As such, information regarding landmark designations for this period, as well as policy, staffing, legal and political issues, are interspersed with more mundane concerns like meetings, lunches, signing appeal letters, dealing with graffiti and stolen plaques, and typing of reports.
  During the years covered by the journals, Goldstone appears to have taken little time off, and as the Commission gains in significance, the journals are completed in shorter periods of time, indicative of the intense pace of the work. In addition to tracing the passage of historic district designations and individual building and monument designations, the journals offer accounts of the fights concerning erection of a tower over Grand Central Station (1968-1969), and describe meetings such as one held at a private home on Park Avenue on February 25, 1971, with many notable people in attendance, to discuss an idea that will apparently become the Central Park Conservancy.
  The journals are arranged in chronological order in Boxes 1 and 2.
  - Journals (Volumes 1-15), 1968-1971 (Box 1)
  - Journals (Volumes 18-30), 1972-1974 (Box 2)
- Series II. Reports
  Another significant portion of this collection consists of copies of reports and related documents. Most are Landmarks Designation Reports produced by the LPC. Box 3, Folder 1, however, contains materials from Goldstone's earlier tenure on the City Planning Commission. Of the three reports included, two reflect Goldstone's dissenting position - an Addition to Flushing Meadow Park (1963) and the Remapping of West Broadway between West 3rd and Washington Square South (1966). In a third decision -- Breezy Point Map Change - Goldstone agreed with the majority but the acting chairman and one other member dissented.
  Box 4, Folder 4 contains a report unrelated to the LPC. The Centreville Courthouse/Multi-Service Center Report was produced in May of 1979 for the State of Maryland by the firms of McLeod Ferrara Ensign and Gruzen and Partners. It describes a project whose goal is to "develop a coordinated series of building projects to house the Court and State agencies systems" for Queen Anne's County, Maryland. Harmon Goldstone served as a consultant on Architectural Styles and Guidelines.
  The remaining folders in this series contain reports related to the designation of landmarks and historic districts. The predominant format is the Landmark Designation Report whose components include particulars of the public hearing(s) held on the proposed designation; detailed description and analysis from an architectural and historical point of view; and a summary of the Commission's findings and designations. Some of the reports contain photographs and/or floor plans. Historic District Designation Reports are lengthier, adding maps and detailed descriptions of individual properties within the district. Associated with some of the reports are summaries, press releases and, in one case (Box 3, Folder 7), a several-page hand-written spreadsheet. There are annotations on a number of the documents, presumably written by Goldstone. Box 3, Folder 5 contains a newspaper clipping which announces the voiding of two designations (included in the same folder) by the Board of Estimate.
  The contents of Box 3, Folders 8, 9 and 10 were formerly housed in a brown folder labeled in Goldstone's hand, "LPC Reports 1976, 1977, 1978 with Questions." Folder 8 contains a few written questions. The other two folders include summary sheets annotated by Goldstone with question marks (?) where reports are missing.
  The materials are arranged chronologically (except for boxes 4-5) and the container list reflects the districts, buildings and/or monuments within each folder. As these reports are all photocopies, their quality is not consistent. Some are very clear while, in others, portions are faint. All, however, are legible.
  Five of the landmarks below are identified with an asterisk (*); they appear on the Landmark Designation Lists but their reports are not included in the collection.
  - City Planning Commission Reports, 1963,1966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Landmarks Preservation Commission Reports (1973): Boerum Hill Historic District, Brooklyn 23 Individual Houses on State Street, Brooklyn Battery Park Control House, State Street and Battery Place, Manhattan 364 Van Duzer Street House, Richmond 390 Van Duzer Street House, Richmond St. Nicholas Russian Orthodox Cathedral, Manhattan (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Landmarks Preservation Commission Reports (Feb-June 1974): St. John's Church, 1331 Bay Street, Richmond 203 Prince Street, Manhattan The Bailey Residence, 10 St. Nicholas Place, Manhattan Andrew Carnegie Mansion, 2 East 91st Street, Manhattan 1009 Fifth Avenue House, Manhattan 998 Fifth Avenue Apartment House, Manhattan Otto Kahn House (Convent of the Sacred Heart), 1 East 91st Street, Manhattan James A. Burden House (Convent of the Sacred Heart), 7 East 91st Street, Manhattan St. Bartholomew's Church, 1227 Pacific Street, Brooklyn Congregation Shearith Israel, 99 Central Park West, Manhattan The Cloisters (Metropolitan Museum of Art), Fort Tryon Park, Manhattan Public Baths, Northeast Corner of East 23rd Street and Asser Levy Place, Manhattan Schinasi Residence, 351 Riverside Drive, Manhattan Central Park, Manhattan Queensboro Bridge 52nd Police Precinct Station House, 3016 Webster Avenue, Bronx (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Landmarks Preservation Commission Reports (July 1974): Carnegie Hill Historic District, Manhattan Grand Army Plaza, Fifth Avenue at 59th Street, Manhattan First Church of Christ Scientist of New York City, 1 West 96th Street, Manhattan 11 East 70th Street House, Manhattan New York Society for Ethical Culture, 2 West 64th Street, Manhattan 15 East 70th Street House, Manhattan 17 East 70th Street House, Manhattan 19 East 70th Street House, Manhattan 21 East 70th Street House, Manhattan 11 East 90th Street House, Manhattan 15 East 90th Street House, Manhattan 17 East 90th Street House, Manhattan 1261 Madison Avenue Apartment House, Manhattan John Henry Hammond House, 9 East 91st Street, Manhattan John B. Trevor House, 11 East 91st Street, Manhattan 1 321 Madison Avenue House, Manhattan 67 East 93rd Street House, Manhattan Lycee Francais de New York, 3 East 95th Street, Manhattan Edith Fabbri House (House of the Redeemer), 7 East 95th Street, Manhattan (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Landmarks Preservation Commission Reports (Sept-Nov 1974): The Lambs Club, 128 West 44th Street, Manhattan Kingsbridge Armory, 29 West Kingsbridge Road, Bronx Fort Tompkins, Hudson Road, Fort Wadsworth Reservation, Richmond The Dorilton, 171 West 71st Street, Manhattan The Frick Collection, 1,5,7 and 9 East 70th Street, Manhattan Bryant Park, 40th to 42nd Street from the Avenue of the Americas to the New York Public Library, Manhattan Gage & Tollner, 372 Fulton Street, Brooklyn The Register/Jamaica Arts Center, 161-04 Jamaica Avenue, Queens Jamaica Savings Bank, 161-02 Jamaica Avenue, Queens First Houses 29, 31, 33-35, 37, 39 and 41 Avenue A; 112-114, 118-120, 124-126, 130-132 and 136-138 3rd Street, Manhattan American Radiator Building, 40 West 40th Street, Manhattan New York Public Library, 476 Fifth Avenue, Manhattan 85 Leonard Street Building, Manhattan Lyceum Theatre, 149-157 West 45th Street, Manhattan Andrew Freeman Home, 1125 Grand Concourse, Bronx Hamilton Heights Historic District, Manhattan (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Landmarks Preservation Commission Reports (Jan-Sept 1975): Central Savings Bank, 2100-2108 Broadway, Manhattan Verdi Square, Broadway at 72nd Street, Manhattan Ocean Parkway, Brooklyn United States Courthouse, Foley Square, Manhattan De Lamar Mansion, 233 Madison Avenue, Manhattan Gage & Tollner, Interior of Ground Floor Dining Room, 373 Fulton Street, Brooklyn Federal Hall National Memorial, 15 Pine Street, Manhattan Bartow-Pell Mansion Museum, Pelham Bay Park, Shore Road, Bronx Morris-Jumel Mansion, West 160th Street and Edgecombe Avenue, Manhattan St. Paul's Memorial Church and Rectory, 225 St. Paul's Avenue, Stapleton, Staten Island Our Lady of Lourdes Roman Catholic Church, 467 West 142nd Street, Manhattan American Museum of Natural History, Central Park West and 79th Street, Manhattan Van Cortlandt Mansion, Broadway and West 242nd Street, Van Cortlandt Park, Bronx Boys' High School, 832 Mercy Avenue, Brooklyn Dry Dock #1, Dock Street at the foot of 3rd Street, Brooklyn Navy Yard, Brooklyn Harlem River Houses, 151st to 153rd Streets, Macombs Place to Harlem River Drive, Manhattan Stuyvesant Square Historic District, Manhattan (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Landmarks Preservation Commission Reports (Nov 1975): Fulton Ferry Historic District, Brooklyn Prospect Park, Brooklyn The Arch and Colonnade of the Manhattan Bridge Approach, Manhattan Bridge Plaza at Canal Street, Manhattan General Grant National Memorial, 122nd Street and Riverside Drive, Manhattan Bayard-Condict Building, 65-69 Bleecker Street, Manhattan, 1975,n.d. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Landmarks Preservation Commission Reports (1976) Lescaze House, 211 East 48th Street, Manhattan Municipal Asphalt Plant, 90th - 91st Street at the East River Drive, Manhattan City Hall, Broadway and City Hall Park, Manhattan Chapel of the Good Shepherd, Roosevelt Island opposite East 68th Street, Manhattan Smallpox Hospital, Roosevelt Island opposite East 52nd Street, Manhattan Strecker Laboratory, Roosevelt Island, opposite East 52nd Street, Manhattan Octagon Tower, Roosevelt Island, opposite East 79th Street, Manhattan Lighthouse, Roosevelt Island, opposite East 86th Street, Manhattan Blackwell House, opposite East 65th Street, Manhattan St. Peter's Church, Chapel and Cemetery, 2500 Westchester Avenue, Bronx Stoothoff-Baxter-Kouwenhoven House, 1640 East 48th Street, Brooklyn Elias Hubbard Ryder House, 1926 East 28th Street, Brooklyn Old Gravesend Cemetery, Brooklyn King Mansion, King Park, Jamaica Avenue and 153rd Street, Queens New York State Supreme Court, Queens County, Long Island City Branch, 25-10 Court Square, Long Island City, Queens Surrogate's Court (Hall of Records), 31 Chambers Street, Manhattan A dministration Building at East 180th Street, 481 Morris Park Avenue, Bronx Gertrude Rhinelander Waldo Mansion, 867 Madison Avenue, Manhattan Bronx County Courthouse, 851 Grand Concourse, Bronx 2876 Richmond Terrace, Mariner's Harbor, Staten Island Towers Nursing Home, 2 West 106th Street, 32 West 106th Street and 455 Central Park West, Manhattan Statue of Liberty National Monument, Liberty Island, Manhattan Soldiers and Sailors Monument, Riverside Park opposite 89th Street, Manhattan Saint Cecelia's Church, 120 East 106th Street, Manhattan Saint Cecelia's Convent, 112 East 106th Street, Manhattan Scribner Building (United Synagogue of America), 153-157 Fifth Avenue, Manhattan Bronx Post Office, 560 Grand Concourse, Bronx 17 West 16th Street House, Manhattan Surgeon's House (Quarters "R-1") Third Naval District, United States Naval Station, Flushing Avenue opposite Ryerson Street, Brooklyn Creedmoor Farmhouse, Bellerose, Queens Cubberly-Britton Cottage, 3737 Richmond Road, Staten Island Stuyvesant Polyclinic Hospital, 137 Second Avenue, Manhattan (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Landmarks Preservation Commission Reports (1977): Oliver Gould Jennings Residence, 7 East 72nd Street, Manhattan Henry T. Sloane Residence, 9 East 72nd Street, Manhattan Barbara Rutherford Hatch Residence, 153 East 53rd Street, Manhattan Prospect Cemetery, 157th Street and Beaver Road, Jamaica, Queens Saint George's Protestant Episcopal Church, 800 March Avenue, Brooklyn Grace Memorial House (Huntington House), 94-96 Fourth Avenue, Manhattan 23rd Regiment Armory, 1322 Bedford Avenue, Brooklyn 83rd Precinct Police Station and Stable, 179 Wilson Avenue, Brooklyn Public School 39, 417 Sixth Avenue, Brooklyn Fort Hamilton Officers' Club, Fort Hamilton Parkway and Shore Parkway, Brooklyn George W. Vanderbilt Residence, 647 Fifth Avenue, Manhattan Pratt-New York Phoenix School of Design, 160 Lexington Avenue, Manhattan Fulton Ferry Historic District, Brooklyn Pier A, Battery Park, Manhattan Parachute Jump, The Riegelmann Boardwalk, West 16th Street and West 19th Street, Coney Island, Brooklyn St. Michael's Chapel of Old St. Patrick's Cathedral, 266 Mulberry Street, Manhattan Fourteenth Ward Industrial School, 256-258 Mott Street, Manhattan 677 Lafayette Avenue House (Magnolia Grandiflora), Brooklyn 678 Lafayette Avenue House (Magnolia Grandiflora), Brooklyn 679 Lafayette Avenue House (Magnolia Grandiflora), Brooklyn Central Park West - West 73rd-74th Street - Historic District, Manhattan Metropolitan Museum Historic District, Manhattan * First Precinct Police Station, South Street and Old Slip, Manhattan Ottendorfer Branch, New York Public Library, 135 Second Avenue, Manhattan Former Lord & Taylor Building, 901 Broadway, Manhattan Williamsburgh Savings Bank, No. 1 Hanson Place, Brooklyn Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue at 82nd Street, Manhattan 45 East 66th Street Building, Manhattan, 1977,n.d. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Landmarks Preservation Commission Reports (Jan-Aug 1978): Paramount Studios, Building No. 1, 35-11 35th Avenue, Astoria, Queens Fleming Smith Warehouse, 451-453 Washington Street, Manhattan Civic Club (Estonian House), 243 East 34th Street, Manhattan Casa Italiana, 1151-1161 Amsterdam Avenue, Manhattan Radio City Music Hall, 50th Street and Avenue of the Americas, Manhattan 208, 210, 212, 214, 216, and 218 East 78th Street Houses, Manhattan A ndrew Norwood House, 241 West 14th Street, Manhattan Knickerbocker Field Club, 114 East 18th Street, Manhattan * 271 Ninth Street House, Brooklyn * Albemarle-Kenmore Terraces Historic District, Brooklyn (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Landmarks Preservation Commission Reports (Sept 1978) Chrysler Building, 405 Lexington Avenue, Manhattan * Chrysler Building Ground Floor Interior * Fort Greene Historic District, Brooklyn Brooklyn Academy of Music Historic District, Brooklyn (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Landmarks Preservation Commission Reports (Nov 1978): Chanin Building, 122 East 42nd Street, Manhattan Former Police Headquarters Building, 240 Centre Street, Manhattan No. 8 Thomas Street Building, Manhattan Fraunces Tavern Block Historic District, Manhattan Town Hall, 113-123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Landmarks Preservation Commission Reports (1979): Racquet & Tennis Club Building, 370 Park Avenue, Manhattan Captain John T. Barker House, 9-11 Trinity Place, Staten Island Robbins and Appleton Building, 1-5 Bond Street, Manhattan (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Report Regarding Landmark Designation of 45 E. 66th Street, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Preliminary Study of NYU Bellevue Hospital, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Feasibility of Alternatives to the Demolition of the Westchester Courthouse, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Feasibility of Alternatives to the Demolition of the Westchester Courthouse, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Greenacre Park, Study by Project for Public Spaces, Inc., 1977 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Centreville Courthouse/Multi-Service Center Report, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Goldstone & Hinz, Architects P.C., 1986 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Series III. Scrapbooks
  This series is composed of personal and professional scrapbooks created either by Harmon Goldstone or a family member spanning from 1906 to 1978. The professional scrapbooks primarily deal with the Landmarks Preservation Commission. His other professional scrapbooks concern the Junior Council of MOMA, Municipal Arts Society, and Goldstone's book, History Preserved: New York City Landmarks and Historic Districts.
  Notable among the personal items is the wedding scrapbook of his parents, Aline May Lewis and Lafayette Anthony Goldstone, who married on June 10, 1908.
  - Personal, 1921-1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Personal, 1928-1952 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Junior Council of MOMA, 1953-1967 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Municipal Arts Society, 1956-1962 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Architectural Work, 1952-1966
  - Architectural Works, 1969-1978 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - City Planning Commission 1, 1961-1963 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - City Planning Commission 2, 1961-1963 (Box 6, Folder 3)